Hi, this is Robert Schreer with another edition of Shere Intelligence, where the intelligence
goes from my guest in this case, an intelligence agent from the CIA. John
Kiriakou was recruited out of George Washington University in Washington by
his professor, went to the CIA, learned Arabic, spent a lot of time in
different places, hotspots of the world, but particularly in the Middle East, and
who was responsible for the capture of what was then alleged to be the number
three a member of al-Qaeda and this was considered a big achievement. He spent many hours with
this fellow until he was turned over to others and the end of the day he was tortured and we've had
a news break in this. Remember as we're getting ready for maybe World War three and we got the
Cold War back with Russia. What happened in the war on terror? We know Afghanistan is a mess
we know Saudi Arabia is as solid as ever with its own convictions and values sometimes murderous
and now the US is going and the West is going to have more on Saudi oil and what happened to this
Warrant Error. Who caused it? What was the account? And we had just the news flash that
we've not had any trials or anything where we might learn who these folks were and what they
did. But five key witnesses, including the one that John was involved in capturing
at Guantanamo, that there's a plea deal. And they might, they won't have a trial where we
could learn something, but they might be held in Guantanamo after all of this torture
and what have you to just die their life so-called naturally.
John, what do you make of it all?
Where are we?
Is this the end of the tale and what do we really know?
Well, rather than being at the end of the beginning,
which we were for many years, it seems,
it looks like now we're at the beginning of the end.
You know, the sad part about this whole situation
that's dragged on now for 20 years.
It was 20 years ago this week that we captured Abu Zubaydah.
The sad part is that there's no justice that will be had in this scenario.
In the end, Abu Zubaydah was not allowed to face his accusers in a court of law.
Well, not just Abu Zubaydah, but Khalid Sheikh Mohammed and the other three.
They were not allowed to face their accusers in a court of law.
They were never charged with a specific crime.
They were never allowed to have a jury of their peers,
judge their behavior.
And so as a result, we'll never really
know what they have to say in this case.
For all these years, these 20 years, the CIA and the Pentagon
have kept their testimony secret, in many cases, top secret.
And I think historically, we're going to be lesser for it.
We'll never know the lessons that could have been learned
because of the 9-11 attacks, because we're not allowed to know them.
Well, just so we don't sound like these conspirators, thesis people that everybody loathes, let
me just say that what you said about not knowing is really what the 9-11 Commission report
told us.
That's right.
assembled by President Bush, and there's a disclaimer in the 9-11 Commission report,
a very honest disclaimer, that the narrative they developed of what this plot was and how
it was carried out was flawed because they were not allowed to talk to the key witnesses,
and that they weren't even allowed to talk.
This is the 9-11 Commission.
These people had the highest security clearance.
They were not allowed to talk to the people in the CIA and elsewhere who interviewed the
key witnesses.
So they were dependent upon stuff that came from basically the torturers through third
party in the government, other things, to develop their narrative.
And one of the virtues, of course, of an open public trial, we might have learned
something about it.
What was their relation to Saudi Arabia?
Why did they do what they're alleged to have done?
And we, you know, for all our claims about being a society of law, these people were tortured
and tell us about it, because you sat there, what was it, 56 hours, yeah, describe that.
So you were in, on the first thing, you were the one who sort of led the capture
and you were guarding him and tell us what happened. He's one of those five that's still
in Guantanamo, still hasn't had a trial, and we still don't know who he was and what was it all about.
Yeah, that's exactly right. I led the raids that resulted in the capture of Abu Zubaydah,
and Abu Zubaydah was the first high-value target that we caught after 9-11. We had killed
Al-Qaeda's, his title was Director of Military Operations, Muhammad Atef. We had killed him
in October of 2001 in a bombing raid in Afghanistan, but we had never actually captured anybody. And so
this was a beta capture was a very big deal. And as you said in your introduction there,
I sat with him after the capture for 56 hours. We spoke at great length. There were certainly
million questions that I had for him that I didn't have the opportunity to ask
because I had to turn him over to CIA colleagues of mine who then took him to
a secret prison but there were a million things that I wanted to ask him and it's
it's kind of a long story I'll be very short with it but the FBI you can go a
you can go a little longer because you were a key witness to this history. You were there when it
was still raw and relatively open before the the control people came in and we never heard from
this guy and by the time we heard from him he'd been driven crazy by all this torture and everything.
That's right. Just introduce us to this high value asset that you, John Carriaco,
actually had captured? Sure. We believed at the time that Abu Zubaydah was the number three
in al-Qaeda. As it turns out, he wasn't the number three, but he was still a very important
component of the al-Qaeda leadership. He was, I guess you could call him al-Qaeda's
logistician. He was the person who had founded the House of Martyrs Safe House for al-Qaeda
in Peshawar, Pakistan. He was the one who founded and ran both of Al-Qaeda's training
camps in southern Afghanistan. If you needed a fake passport or an airplane ticket or cash
or anything, it was Abu Zubaydah who secured those things for you. Now, he always claimed
that he was not a part of the planning of 9-11. In retrospect, that was probably
true, but what he was able to provide us was at least as important as an account of the
planning for 9-11.
What Abu Zubaydah ended up giving an FBI agent by the name of Ali Soufan was first and foremost
Al-Qaeda's wiring diagram.
We just didn't know what Al-Qaeda looked like below the leadership.
We knew that Osama bin Laden had created the group.
We knew that the number two was Aiman Azawahadi, formerly of Egyptian Islamic Jihad, who had
merged his group with bin Laden's and took the number two spot.
We knew that Muhammad Atef was the head of military operations.
And we knew that there was a very bad man out there by the name, or by the nom
to Ger, I should say, of Muhtar. And I can get to that in a minute. But we didn't know
anything beyond that. We didn't know, for example, how Al-Qaeda had set up its various
cells around the world. We didn't know where those cells were. We didn't know how Al-Qaeda
foot soldiers communicated with their leaders. We didn't know how they sent money. We
didn't know how they sent operational instructions to one another. We didn't know anything
about the planning. And so Abu Zubaydah was able to tell us how that was all structured.
For example, we could ask a question like this. Let's say Al Qaeda wanted to conduct an operation
in Dusseldorf. How would you go about that? And Abu Zubaydah would answer that, well,
there's one guy named Muhammad, and Muhammad lives at this address, and Muhammad has
access to weapons and he has a friend named Abdullah and this is Abdullah's phone number
and Abdullah has access to explosives and they stay at an apartment that's owned by Rashid.
And this is Rashid's email address so that he told you all this without torture
In fact, the only usable information that came out of him or any other prisoner was without torture was without torture
And that's really the key here
This is what he was telling Ali Sufan the FBI agent who just sat across from Abu Zubaydah at a table
Treated him with respect gave him an occasional cigarette or an apple or a cup of tea and
and established a rapport with him this this really did work and so he gave us
that wiring diagram and then he told us about Muhtar now we knew that Muhtar
was instrumental in the planning of the 9-11 attacks but that's all we knew and
we had no idea what his name was I remember Abu Zubaydah laughing
because he couldn't believe that we didn't know that Muhtar was Khaled
Sheikh Mohammed. And so that was revelatory for us who had gone to school in North Carolina
before he became a terrorist, right? That's right. And who spoke English as well as you and I.
And so we at least then knew where we needed to look. We needed to look for for Muhtar's trail.
He was probably in Pakistan somewhere, perhaps in Afghanistan, and thanks to Abu Zubaydah,
thanks to Ali Soufan getting it from Abu Zubaydah, we found Khalid Sheikh Mohammed in a safe house
in Raul Pindi, Pakistan in August of 2002. Now, what ended up happening was there was great
professional jealousy at the CIA because the FBI was taking the lead in carrying out these
interrogations. The reason the FBI was taking the lead was because 9-11 was still an open
criminal investigation and because the FBI was highly skilled in these kinds of interrogations.
They had been doing it since the Nuremberg trials in 1946. And so the CIA, because it was so angry
and upset. The director, George Tennant at the time, went to see President Bush and told
President Bush that the CIA just had to take over primacy of this interrogation. President
Bush made a terrible mistake and agreed to pull out Ali Soufan and the rest of the
FBI contingent and to allow the CIA to take over.
the FBI didn't believe in torture, and the CIA did. They brought in the torturers. And,
you know, so talk about that because that led to your disillusionment with the CIA. So,
you know, this is the real issue. We know we have that we can't read the Senate report
that was done when I am five, so I would tell this committee. And how many pages is
that report? It's about 50,000 pages. And what was finally released to the public? It's almost
embarrassing to say. It was just a 500 page, a very heavily redacted 500 page executive summary
of the actual report. We'll never get to see what the actual report looks like. Never.
At least the introduction, though, of the summary makes it clear that no usable information was
obtained with torture. You know, we expect countries all over the world, now very prominently
Putin's Russia, to be accountable for their actions and their human rights violations and
so forth. That's our message. We are never held accountable for ours. Here was, yes,
this massive use of torture in the name of making it safer. It did not produce any
usable information. They brought in these guys who justified it on some kind of pseudo-scientific
basis. And here we are now at the end of the chapter with these five key witnesses including
the one that you captured still sitting in Guantanamo and we don't know anything more really
about them and what they did. They've never been able to testify to what they did, explain
their actions any more than you did in your FBI counterpart going back to the beginning.
So torture didn't work, I'd say inhuman, but there's no accountability. And these guys still
will not have their trial. Why not? You are absolutely right. And that's what the real
shame of this entire situation is. They will never have their trial because the CIA is afraid,
rightfully afraid that they will talk about the torture that they underwent. Torture that was
a crime, not just in the United States, but an international crime, as the United States is
a signatory to the United Nations Convention Against Torture. They're afraid that they will reveal
information that the CIA considers to still be classified. They're afraid that they'll talk
about CIA sources and methods, that they'll talk about the torture program and what they
suffered through, and they just don't want to take a chance that any of that information
will ever become public.
In the Senate torture report, in the executive summary that we spoke about a moment ago,
there's a footnote there that is so important, it bears raising right now in this conversation.
It says that even though Abu Zubaydah was not a member of al-Qaeda, even though Abu Zubaydah
had never pledged fealty to Osama bin Laden, even though Abu Zubaydah never directly committed
any crime against Americans or American installations, he will never be allowed to leave Guantanamo
ever. And the footnote goes on to say that when he dies, the CIA will cremate his body
and will throw his ashes in the Caribbean. Well, that's not justice. And that's not the
American way. If this man is as bad as we say he is, then let's give him his day in
court because whether we like his politics or not, that's what the Constitution says
that he gets and we've never given him that. Time for a break and we'll be back in a few minutes.
We're back with your intelligence and our guests. How long are we going to pretend
it's not the American way? My goodness, you know, because what you're really talking about
is denying the public information that it needs to have about why bad things
happen. And you can go back and that's why they say in a war truth is the first
casualty. We can try to examine you know the dropping of the atomic bombs in
Hiroshima, the Gulf of Tonkin which was the excuse for expanding the war.
And you don't get the information unless some whistleblower comes along and there are very
few and far between Daniel Ellsberg to you, there's what, 14 or 18 in between, you know,
and so tell us about your whistleblowing because you didn't go along with the torture,
You didn't openly expose it until you were out and you did it in a way that actually
tried to advance the discussion, didn't make anybody weaker or threaten anyone, nothing
like the making of the movie Zero Dark Thirty where the producers were allowed to meet the
people or hear and get the names of the people who killed Bin Laden, you know, putting
their life at risk.
That's exactly right.
You know, this all took place in 2002.
At least the beginning of the torture took place in 2002.
And just before, months before it began, let me clarify that.
I returned to CIA headquarters in May of 2002.
And immediately upon my return, I was asked if I wanted to be trained, quote, in the
use of enhanced interrogation techniques.
I had never heard that term before.
And when it was explained to me, I objected.
And I said, this is a torture program.
I said, I have a moral and ethical problem with this,
and I don't want to have anything to do with it.
Well, I was labeled as the human rights guy, which
was not a compliment.
And I moved on to a different position.
Well, that was May of 2002.
On August 1, 2002, the CIA began to torture Abuzabeta.
And as they captured additional high-value targets,
they began to torture those high-value targets as well
in a series of secret prisons placed all around the world.
Well, as it happened, I had been promoted
when I got home from Pakistan.
And I was given a position as the executive assistant
to the CIA's deputy director for operations.
And in that position, I had access
to literally everything that the CIA was doing around the world, and I'm reading these reports
of torture that are coming back.
And I thought to myself, surely people are going to see how patently illegal this is.
Somebody's going to go public.
Instead, what happened was certainly some people at the secret site were upset.
even repulsed by what they were seeing.
Some of them wrote cables back saying
that watching Abu Zubaydah be tortured made them vomit,
one woman fainted, one doctor complained,
this is not why I joined the CIA.
I joined the CIA to serve my country,
not to participate in this.
And I thought, OK, this is great
because so many people are upset,
somebody is going to say something.
and then nobody said anything.
A couple people curtailed their assignments,
meaning they said, I can't work here anymore
and they came back home.
That's a career ending decision.
But nobody went public.
And so I left the CIA about two years later,
still waiting for somebody to go public.
And then finally in December of 2007,
five and a half years after Abu Zubaydah was tortured for the first time,
I decided that I would say something. I was approached by Brian Ross of ABC News
and I decided that I would tell him the truth. He had heard from other people that there was
a torture program but nobody would confirm it on camera and so I confirmed it on camera in
December of 2007. I believed at the time that the American people had a right to know. I
believe that the American people own the information and they have a right to know what the CIA
is doing in their name. And I also believed that it was illegal for the CIA to classify
the torture program in the first place because it's illegal to classify a crime.
You can't put a classification on a program that is illegal to begin with.
That's a felony.
And so I decided to go public and to tell what I knew.
Now, you're right.
I said in that ABC News interview that I believed we should have a national conversation
about a torture program.
We should decide as a country, as a nation, if this is who we want to be, do we want
be the bully that we complain about when we see other countries doing it, or do we want to be that
shining beacon that Ronald Reagan always bragged about, a beacon of hope for human rights and civil
rights and civil liberties, because we can't be both. They're mutually exclusive.
Okay, but you said that and you didn't get in trouble yet. And that's when George Bush was,
I want to be clear about this, George Bush was president and they didn't bring an action
against you.
No, the day after the ABC News interview, the CIA filed something called a Crimes Report
against me with the FBI saying that I had exposed classified information and violation
of the Espionage Act.
And so, from December of 2007 to December of 2008, at the tail end of the George W.
Bush administration, the FBI investigated me.
And they did it for a whole year.
And then in December of 2008, they sent my attorneys something called a declination letter,
saying that they were declining to prosecute me because they did not believe that I had
revealed classified information.
And then off the record, one of the FBI agents told my attorney that the torture program was
the worst kept secret in Washington.
So we were so excited.
My wife and I actually went out to dinner that night to celebrate that this dark cloud
that had hung over my head for a year had finally disappeared.
Your wife, who I'd been in, was in the CIA.
Correct.
My wife was also a senior CIA officer and was still in the CIA at the time.
What I didn't know, well, there were two things that I didn't know, one of which I only learned
very recently.
What I didn't know was that four weeks later, when Barack Obama became president, and John
Brennan became the deputy national security advisor for counterterrorism, and later CIA
director.
This is the guy who shows up on MSNBC all the time, all the time, talking hand on
Darling of liberals now. That's right. Well, John Brennan asked the Justice Department to secretly reopen the case against me
So I had no idea that for the next four years
from
January of
2009 or three years rather January of 2009 to January of 2012
That my phones were being tapped that my emails were being monitored and that teams of FBI agents had surveillance on me
And so in January of this is because now I want to be clear because you know most
of the people I know are Democrats and they think Democrats are never warm
mongers and they never could cover up for torture and so forth and this was
the this was the Obama Biden administration and maybe you know
people like Rachel Maddow on MSNBC could ask John Brennan why did you do
this. The FBI didn't think this guy had done anything wrong or the Bush administration didn't.
Why did you, why did you do this? You know, they didn't do it against General Petraeus,
who I know was head of the CIA and he turned over his black briefing books for the president,
the highest secrets to his mistress. Right. He got a slap on the wrist for this. Didn't
serve any time. You served two years, had your life destroyed. He didn't lose his pension.
You lost your pension. Your whole life was wrecked, you know, the making of the whistleblower.
So you know, how does this happen? Where is our collective memory? Why don't we, well,
think about it. I mean, I mean, Barack Obama moved against more people under the Espionage
that all President is before him combined.
Well, let's talk about that because that's a very important point.
The Espionage Act was written and passed into law in 1917
to combat German saboteurs during the First World War.
Between 1917 and 2009, it was used three times
to try Americans who had spoken with the media.
media, three times in almost a century. In the eight years of the Obama presidency, eight
people, all of whom were whistleblowers, were arrested and charged with espionage for speaking
to the media. So almost three times the number of all previous presidents combined. There's
just no excuse for that. None. Barack Obama, for all of his reputation as a progressive,
had a positively Nixonian obsession with national security leaks and was willing to use the
iron fist that is the Espionage Act to clamp down on those leaks.
And so you were facing a very long sentence.
Forty-five years is what I was facing.
And in fact, that was the Justice Department's first offer, was 45 years.
And one of the attorneys, a woman, one of the Justice Department attorneys said, take
a plea to a espionage charge, Mr. Kiriakou, and you might live to meet your grandchildren.
That's how it started.
And then, you know, yeah, it was, I went home.
No, that's cold.
Yeah.
I'll tell you what's colder.
It's something that I just learned in the last couple of months, that the whole time
that I was going through this, my now ex-wife was reporting back to the CIA's Office
of Security all of my plans.
I would meet with my lawyers and I would tell her, well, here's our strategy.
And she would call the CIA and tell them what my legal strategy was.
She admitted to that in open court six weeks ago.
So this is, you know, our fear of totalitarian societies that the real it's return husband
against wife and children against their parents.
real and and you know what you're saying is is so chilling because you know I'm
one of those people who was enthusiastic for Obama I even have still
have the artist design t-shirts that cost me 500 bucks and everything when I
sure contribution row columns saying how great was and obviously I still
think it's great that we have a non-white male president but you know
I don't feel it's so great that we have Clarence Thomas on the Supreme Court.
So you hope that the promise of Obama would be something progressive.
And we never examined this.
That's why I'm doing this.
I'm trying to examine how this happens and why we look the other way.
And one reason we do this, and this is where George Rawel is 1984.
So important is that need for an enemy.
And once we locate the enemy and you can change the enemies,
You could swap them around, but you know right now we don't know whether it's communist China or
Communist Russia led by Putin. But they're almost interchangeable at this point. You have to have
the enemy. And once you find the enemy, truth, decency, honor, common sense, all of that gets
sacrificed. And there you got swept up in it. And I want to mention the irony that you couldn't
find a job. You lost your pension, you have five children, you're expected to provide support,
and you end up working for an almost non-existent Russian-sponsored radio station called Sputnik,
which has an outlet in Kansas that goes about four blocks, I gather, before it gets garbled
by everybody else's signal, and you've got a small station in Washington, and that's the
That's the only way you can scratch a living here and even that station lets you denounce
Putin's invasion, you know, that station gave you a contract in which you explicitly
had the right to criticize Putin and criticize Russia.
So you haven't had a bad experience with that station.
Now everybody would like you to resign and what, starve, starve for being a whistleblower
and not have a voice.
ironic is that, right? You know, when I went to prison in the end for 23 months, the government's
best and final offer was three and a half years. And I said, you know what, I was just so,
I was so depressed to the point of being suicidal, I just didn't care anymore.
I said, you know what, I'm going to roll the dice and go to trial. And when I go to trial,
I'm going to testify on my own behalf. And I might accidentally mention some of the horrible crimes
against humanity and war crimes that I witnessed in 15 years at the CIA. And then we'll just see
how the cards fall. And then they came back, okay, okay, 30 months, you do 23. So that was the final
deal. Um, but you're right. They stripped away your financial stability, your ability to get a job or
anything. Yeah. Well, not only did they, did they confiscate my pension, which was worth $700,000.
They forced me to spend $1.1 million, most of which I didn't have on attorney's fees. They
literally quite literally bankrupted me. So I was ruined financially. And then when I got home from
prison two years later, I literally could not find a job anywhere. I was turned down at Target,
at McDonald's, at Safeway. I literally could not find a job anywhere. And then finally,
I got an offer of my own radio show at Sputnik News, the Russian government news service.
and I turned it down. I turned it down because I said, well, I can't in good conscience work for
the Russians. Seven or eight months later, they approached me a second time and they said, look,
we'd really like to give you your own show. And I said, well, if I'm going to work for you guys,
I would need a guarantee that I can say anything I want to say and I can criticize anybody I
want to criticize, including Vladimir Putin. And without missing a beat, the general manager said,
done. And I said, it was in your contract, right? Well, I said, are you willing to put it in writing?
He said, yes. I said, put it in my contract. He said, done. A day later, I had a contract.
It's in writing. I've been doing my own show there now for five years. And on the day,
just to give you as an example, on the day of the Russian invasion, I started my show by
saying that I wholeheartedly condemn Russia's invasion of Ukraine. I don't care what their
reasons are. No country has the right to cross a border into another country's territory and
that Russians need to withdraw immediately from all Ukrainian territory. And I've been
saying that every day since the invasion began and never once has anybody objected
to it or even asked me to tone it down. Never.
Yeah, but you are finished. Yeah, you know, all your training, all your knowledge. I mean,
let's, we didn't even go into that, that you were in Baran. You know what's going on in Saudi
Arabia. You know the world. You're very incredibly smart. You've written important books. But
at all somebody has to say, it's like the old black list.
Oh, he was on Sputnik.
Boom, you're not a human being anymore
because they feel so virtuous.
The same people, by the way, who destabilized the Ukraine,
these glorious Democrats administration,
you know, they taken over the State Department.
So they effectively, you know, undermined
and helped this guy who was able to get along
Russia get thrown out back in, you know, 12 years ago. And no, sorry, eight years ago.
Eight years ago.
And, yeah. And they always feel self-righteous. That's what I want to get at here. I'm talking
to a guy who was destroyed by Barack Obama. Let's just put it, and Biden, who was in
that administration, destroyed for telling us the truth about terror and torture and all the
things we spend all of these resources, all get the bad guys, bad guys. He got the bad
guy. He was able to get more of the information. The only valuable information was gotten by
people like John Kiryako, who did not engage in torture, made us safer. And he dared to
confirm that we have a torture program. That's what he's a whistleblower told us.
We had a torture program. Then the Senate spent what was it, six years investigating
the Senate Intelligence Committee they were locked in a room in a CIA building not allowed to take
anything out and there's a great movie the report which everyone should watch about how hard it was
to get this material out and they finally there I'll say something positive about Democrats it was
the Democrats on the committee the Republicans didn't join in under Diane Feinstein who get this
report, and the report has never been made public to us. So for all the talk about transparency,
democracy, and so forth, we don't even know how many copies there are and where they are.
That's a good point. We don't know how many copies there are. The conventional wisdom here in
Washington is that the CIA produced 10 copies, right? One went to the White House, to the
office of the executive office of the president, one went to the office of the vice president,
one went to the national security council, DOD, state, CIA, FBI, NSA, one or two copies
otherwise. But the CIA has never given up ownership of the information. And so even
if those copies are housed in safes in these respective departments and agencies, they actually
belong to the CIA. And there was a news report about three years ago saying that the CIA had begun to
destroy them. Well, if they only exist in hard copy form, and they're destroyed, that information
is lost forever. And there are generations of Americans who haven't even been born yet who
will never have any idea the crimes that the CIA committed in the name of counterterrorism.
Not just the CIA, the American government. They knew, they knew, they, they, you know,
come on, it was the Justice Department and John Woo and those people who all said it was legal.
You know, there's no accountability. And we pride ourselves on the open
society. And then you can have a report six years in preparation done by your
Senate Intelligence Committee and the public never gets to read it. There's no
accountability. And then you have the rare whistleblowers, you're clearly one. But Daniel
Ellsberg, there was the Pentagon Papers and told us the truth about what Vietnam War was about.
And tens of thousands of people knew the truth. They never said a word about it.
You know, their careers got in the way of the truth, you know, or their fear of the
government got in the way of the truth. He told the truth. And he also faced something
like 137 years. I forget the number now. Now it's supposed to be a witness at that trial because I
knew something about Vietnam and been there some time. But the fact of the matter is,
we're so self-righteous. You know, we are, everything else is fake news. Anything embarrassing
to the US government is fake news. Everything that undermines our patriotism is fake news.
But you can spin a tale about the Vietnam War or the Iraq War, the New York Times,
which was the leading media outlet for spreading the lie that there were weapons of mass destruction
in Iraq, they come out scot-free. Everybody, oh, New York Times, that's not fake news,
that's real journalism, you know. And then, you know, the same thing here on the torture report.
Nobody talks about, you know, what we've done in this war on torture, you know, and smashing,
right? Most recently we had a report how they practiced smashing a prisoner's head against
the walls and it could do it to other prisoners, consciously openly smashing his head against
the wall.
You know and there's no accountability. No one has gone to jail for that and the people who supported it and lied about it
They've all been honored and given promotions and then they picked the one guy, you know
Let's wrap this up with that John Kiriakou the one guy who
Said yes, this happened and then you go to jail and your life is destroyed
That's the fate of the whistleblower and and then you were praising our way of life our system of government
our Constitution. Yeah, you know, the whistleblowers should be protected according to the body of the
Constitution, the separation of hours as well as the amendments, but they're not. We have a what?
We've had all of the whistleblowers that I know of. I interviewed quite a few of them. They don't
come to more than a dozen or so in this area. And they've all had their lives destroyed,
Their income destroyed, you know, you think of a guy like Benny at the NSA and he tells
us the truth and they bust into his shower when he's naked there, you know, and they're
going to arrest him.
This guy had worked his whole life in the national security establishment.
So maybe that's the way to wrap this up.
Give you the last word here, John Carriaco, an American hero and my money for my money.
Thank you.
And thank you for raising these issues.
You know, time has passed since this all began.
It's been 20 years, as I said, 20 years this week.
And there aren't a lot of people talking about this, but these questions have never been answered.
This information has never been made public, so thank you for keeping it out there and
keeping it current.
I think that you're doing a public service, and this is very important.
Yeah, but you know what, we're not going to reach that many people.
Let's cut to the chase here.
We always hear that.
You do good work, and yeah, and there's a public service.
The fact of the matter is Daniel Ellsberg's revelations
were not able to stop the Vietnam War.
And you know, we're right now legitimately horrified,
say, by what the Russians are doing in Ukraine
and killing civilians.
You wanna compare that to the carpet bombing of Vietnam.
You wanna compare that to the bombing
of Japan and Germany in the war.
I mean, but at least that was a full scale war, you know.
But what Ellsberg revealed in the Pentagon Papers,
a war that never made any sense.
And the conservative estimates,
McNamara once said he would be considered a war criminal
if the wrong side had won.
And with three and a half million,
he admitted to that died there, mostly civilians.
Now to figure, people think we're throwing Cambodia,
you know, and Laos and so forth,
probably between five and six, seven million
died in a war that no one could make sense of, you know, we tore apart the whole Mideast
or some area you know more about than probably anybody I could talk to for no rhyme or reason
that made sense. And there's no accountability. We have this illusion that we are accountable
and we're not. This is Rome. This is Rome. And they can cover it with fancy language.
They can cover it with manners, but it's Rome on a rampage, you know?
And that's really what's happening.
The incredible assertion of the American prerogative, American power, and anything America does
somehow is morally justifiable.
Disagree?
I couldn't agree more.
I think you're exactly right.
All right.
Let's wrap it up then.
That's it for this edition of Sheer Intelligence.
I want to thank John Kiriakou, a very brave,
a broke human being, I mean financially, not spiritually.
I want to thank the folks at KCRW,
the FM station in Santa Monica, the NPR station
for putting this on, Christopher Ho, and the others.
Joshua Sheer, our executive producer,
Natasha Kimi Zapata, who does the introduction,
Lucy Berber, who does the transcription.
and the JKW Foundation in the memory of a very strong, independent writer, journalist,
Jean Stein for helping support these shows.
See you next week with another edition of Sheer Intelligence.